Markham Starr collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2. 2015 accrual: Against the Tide, Down On The Farm, In History's Wake, and Voices From The Waterfront photographs, March 26, 2005 through December 4, 2013, afc2013031_dc002; 841 TIFF, 4 pdf, 4 xls, and 1 m2t
  - Subseries 3. In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI files, April 8, 2008 through 2010, 264 TIFF, 1 pdf, 1 xls
    - Luke Wheeler and his daughter stand at the conveyor, sorting fish from the day's catch, April 27, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Luke Wheeler and his daughter stand at the conveyor, sorting fish from the day's catch. As a boy, Luke began lobstering from a skiff with his father on the rocky shores of Aquidneck Island. A graduate of Maine Maritime, he chose to fish rather than pursue a career on other types of commercial vessels. Luke also owns and operates the Shirley Ann, a day boat he fishes from the Point when done with the day's trapping.
    - Totes of newly-landed fish, separated by species, await boxing, October 15, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Totes of newly-landed fish, separated by species, await boxing. Few Americans will purchase a whole fish such as these anymore. Once docks brimmed with people waiting to pick the fish they would eat for dinner, but consumers are now far more likely to pull a box from the local grocer's freezer. Today, less than 10 percent of the fish we consume in this country comes from local waters.
    - Crewmembers weigh fish with this hanging scale before placing them in shipping cartons, April 27, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Crewmembers weigh fish with this hanging scale before placing them in shipping cartons. Seemingly old and tired, this scale, like all commercial scales, is calibrated periodically by governmental inspectors. The tangible sense of history and tradition etched into the chipped paint on its ancient face adds a certain elegance missing from its modern digital counterparts.
    - Deckhands chat as they head towards the day's work aboard the Maria Mendonsa, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Deckhands chat as they head towards the day's work aboard the Maria Mendonsa. While most of a trap crew's time is spent fishing, they must also attend to other tasks throughout the summer season. On this day, crewmembers will remove twine from the trap near the Sakonnet Point Lighthouse. Two in middle left to right: Dan MacDonald, Aaron Taylor.
    - Alan Wheeler gets ready to hook onto netting they will remove through the course of the day's work, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Alan Wheeler gets ready to hook onto netting they will remove through the course of the day's work. This day, like those on which they deploy traps in the spring, is another in which the entire crew must pay close attention to dangers surrounding them. Adam Lotz left, Alan Wheeler right.
    - It will be a long and gloomy day of rain as the crew removes twine, although this hardly affects their spirits, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      It will be a long and gloomy day of rain as the crew removes twine, although this hardly affects their spirits. Wearing a uniform of foul weather gear even on sunny days, they hardly notice the additional water falling from above.
    - Squid on deck, May 22, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Squid on deck. These cephalopods have enormous eyes, the giant squid having the largest of any animal alive. Propelled by jets of water, they capture their prey within their eight arms and twin tentacles before tearing them apart with a sharp, beak-like mouth. Not only can squid blend into their surrounds by varying the color and patterning on their skin, they also generate clouds of black ink to help them elude predators.
    - Fishermen remove twine from the frame, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Fishermen remove twine from the frame. Hauling the net vertically using the ship's winch, crewmen pin it to the rail while the portion above is lowered to the deck, allowing another bight of netting to be raised from the sea. As the twine is brought aboard, the cast weights that held the lower edge of the net to the ocean floor are removed. Early on, fishermen used stones to keep twine in place, although these were quickly replaced as weights cast in metal became cheaper. While iron became the standard, even lead was used when economical. Today, when older weights are lost, substitutions are made with ready-made objects such as links from navy anchor chain. Cast concrete weights are occasionally used, but they "float" more than their denser counterparts and are relegated to sections near rocky beaches where they are more likely to be lost.
    - The marine growth fouling this net is obvious, as is the rather wet nature of the day's work, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The marine growth fouling this net is obvious, as is the rather wet nature of the day's work. It will take the crew several hours to bring aboard all of the trap's twine. In skiff left to right: Sammy Peters, Dan MacDonald.
    - The crew from the North Star loads a leader net into a skiff on yet another dreary day, June 4, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The crew from the North Star loads a leader net into a skiff on yet another dreary day. Twine is usually pulled for inspection and cleaning during lulls in the fishing or if threatened by hurricanes. Ian and Sam pull spider crabs from the mesh as they go, a job far more tedious than one might imagine. Sam Willis left, Ian Campbell right.
    - Tom Hoxsie secures the leader line as Sam and Ian work to reattach the twine, June 4, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Tom Hoxsie secures the leader line as Sam and Ian work to reattach the twine. Tom's traps have provided meals of fresh seafood, bait for other fishermen, and live fish for aquariums around the country. Additionally, a local artist gathers subjects for his Japanese fish prints from Tom's traps because each specimen is undamaged when caught this way.
    - Adam Lotz overlooks the crew as they latch onto the twine, April 9, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Adam Lotz overlooks the crew as they latch onto the twine. Adam, a partner in the company, is responsible for the marketing end of the business as well. Beyond their skills as fishermen, a detailed knowledge of when and where to sell their catch is required to assure financial success. The company's product may travel the Eastern Seaboard, and Adam decides when and where it will go.
    - Sam Willis works to reattach the leader's twine to the Breakwater Village trap at the east end of the harbor, June 4, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Sam Willis works to reattach the leader's twine to the Breakwater Village trap at the east end of the harbor. While Tom's traps may be the smallest, this image provides a feeling for just how big they are still. The skiff is only two-thirds the distance to the shore end of the leader. Tom hires Joe Whaley, a retired local fisherman, to do much of the repair work on his nets, although many of his own hours are spent at this task off-season. The twine itself represents a significant expense, not only for the inherent material costs, but for the labor involved when constructing a trap. Anthony Parascandolo estimated building a full-sized trap from scratch would now take two men nearly six months, working six days a week at that.
    - A longboat from the Christine Roberta stops to repair a cut leader, July 14, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A longboat from the Christine Roberta stops to repair a cut leader. Inexperienced yachtsmen, flooding the coast during the summer months, represent a continuous problem for trap fishermen. Although each trap's exact position is marked on charts and hundreds of floats, barrels, and radar buoys make them visible, both sail and speedboats manage to run afoul. Yachtsmen cut their way out of their mistakes, leaving extra work and lost profits in their wakes.
    - Alan Wheeler supervises the deck work as a section of netting comes aboard, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Alan Wheeler supervises the deck work as a section of netting comes aboard. Concern over getting this task done safely left him uncharacteristically tense throughout the day, but having done it hundreds of times before, the job ran smoothly and without incident. Among the many other things to think about in the course of a day's fishing, all captains worry over the safety of their crew.
    - Dan MacDonald and Sammy Peters remove twine from the frame, June 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Dan MacDonald and Sammy Peters remove twine from the frame. Sammy, 87 years old, was the most senior man working traps during this particular season. Despite heart problems and several bouts with cancer, he drove to Sakonnet Point from Massachusetts to arrive at 5:30 each morning, usually the first of the crew on the scene. Left to right: Dan MacDonald, Sammy Peters.
    - View of a trap net stretched in an open field for cleaning and repair, June 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      View of a trap net stretched in an open field for cleaning and repair. John Sousa works at a point almost exactly in the middle of the leader, which stretches to the truck at the far end of the field. Because the loss of twine during the summer can mean financial ruin, each trap company maintains spare twine that can replace netting catastrophically damaged during the fishing season.
    - John Sousa's hands have built and repaired untold thousands of yards of netting throughout his long career, June 16, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      John Sousa's hands have built and repaired untold thousands of yards of netting throughout his long career. This is one of the important skills young fishermen no longer learn, as companies can no longer afford to employ them throughout the year. Corey Wheeler Forrest has learned many of these skills by working with older fishermen and also spends time repairing twine in the hot summer sun.
    - The Eagle rests at her mooring as the sun begins to burn through the early morning fog, July 14, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Eagle rests at her mooring as the sun begins to burn through the early morning fog. As with most harbors, the number of working watercraft continues to dwindle, with pleasure boats filling the moorings left behind. This harbor is no different, as evidenced by the large yacht club just completed next to the trap companies' operations.
    - Portrait of Dan MacDonald, April 27, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Portrait of Dan MacDonald. Alan Wheeler loves to ski and works at a resort in the winter months up north. Dan is one of the snow-makers Alan brings south for the summer to work as crew on the Maria Mendonsa. For men and women who prefer to work outside, trap fishing provides the opportunity to fish without having to go offshore on extended trips.
    - Sully holds the longboats alongside the Mendonsa as she steams to the next trap, June 19, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Sully holds the longboats alongside the Mendonsa as she steams to the next trap. The water jetting from the ship's hull was used as coolant for the vessel's power plant. In this closed system, cold seawater passes through a heat exchanger mounted on the engine block before it is discharged back overboard. Alfred Sullivan.
    - Ian Campbell sits in the rain as the boat heads to the East Wall trap, August 6, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Ian Campbell sits in the rain as the boat heads to the East Wall trap. Two of North Star's leaders begin on the massive stonework forming the Harbor of Refuge. Construction on these breakwaters, nearly 13,000 feet in length, began in 1891 and finished in 1914, providing a safe haven for vessels traveling the coast. Using several million tons of stone, the breakwaters are 20 feet wide at the top and rise in places from waters 34 feet deep.
    - Anthony Parascandolo operates the ship's winch, lifting another load of scup from the sea, May 3, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Anthony Parascandolo operates the ship's winch, lifting another load of scup from the sea. In many ways, fishermen are much like farmers, even ignoring the obvious parallels in food production. Weather and other elements beyond their control often affect their livelihoods. In a few critical summer months, drastic changes in environmental conditions can seriously impact their ability to make a living. As with New England's farmers, fishermen are dependent on specific and expensive equipment to make thin profit margins work, and maintaining that equipment adds much to the overall cost. Finally, trap fishermen and farmers were once major food producers for the area, and both are rapidly disappearing from the Northeast.
    - Tom Hinckley and Saul Umana work together to keep their side of the parlor's twine above water, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Tom Hinckley and Saul Umana work together to keep their side of the parlor's twine above water. The netting used in traps is dipped in liquid tar, giving it a distinctive black color. Early on, tar preserved the cotton fibers from which twine was made. While twine made of nylon won't rot, this added layer of protection helps to reduce physical wear as well as UV damage from sunlight. Left to right: Tom Hinckley, Saul Umana.
    - Portrait of Rick Cambio, June 5, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Portrait of Rick Cambio. A career fisherman, Rick has worked on traps and as a draggerman far out to sea. This summer, after finishing the morning's work, Rick went to work cutting apart a wooden dragger that was no longer commercially viable. Point Judith's fleet has dwindled significantly over the course of the past ten years.
    - Adam and Sully clean the deck while James rests in the longboat, June 19, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Adam and Sully clean the deck while James rests in the longboat. While younger crewmen generally chat on the way to the site, the more experienced members on deck seem always in motion, taking care of little details that assure a smooth day of fishing. Fish species appear at the same time each year with great predictability, as a trap fisherman of 1871 relates: "In the remarks of Mr. E. W. Whalley, of Narragansett Pier, we find a statement of the usual sequence of fish at Point Judith, and are presented at the same time with a most charming fragment of folk-lore. In reply to the inquiry as to whether fish were not earlier arrived at that point than usual, he replied: "About the same. They expected them in February and got the seines ready. They had them in the water in March. I always judge by the dandelions. When I see the first dandelion, scup come in; I watch the buds, and when the buds are swelled full then our traps go in; when the dandelion goes out of bloom and goes to seed, the scup are gone. That is true one year with another, though they vary with the season. I am guided by the blossoms of other kinds of plants for other fish. When high blackberries are in bloom we catch striped bass that weigh from 12 to 20 pounds. When the blue violets are in blossom—they come early—you can catch the small scoot-bass. That has always been my rule; that has been handed down by my forefathers." Left to right on deck: Adam Lotz, Alfred Sullivan.
    - Bucky Smith holds the twine in place as he waits for the signal to begin hauling, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Bucky Smith holds the twine in place as he waits for the signal to begin hauling. Commercial fishing is a rigorous game, better suited to the young and strong. With an average age of 55, a significant portion of New England's fishermen are now approaching retirement, leaving the industry with challenges in this arena as well. Captains often complain the trade is no longer passed to younger generations; finding young men or women with even the most basic skills has become nearly impossible. Roland Smith (Bucky).
    - Christine Roberta at her dock with thousands of pounds of scup in her pens, May 3, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Christine Roberta at her dock with thousands of pounds of scup in her pens. A conveyor will lift these fish into the packing building on the right. Trap companies in Rhode Island do not process their catch beyond simply packing them with ice into waterproof boxes. Others clean and fillet the fish later in the process of getting them to consumers.
    - Ian Campbell and Tom Hoxsie pull twine on the East Wall set, June 4, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Ian Campbell and Tom Hoxsie pull twine on the East Wall set. Tom, who has been trap fishing for more than twenty-five years, feels there may be a better future in harvesting fish by trap than by trawler. Low overhead and a green footprint could help revive the industry. Ian Campbell left, Tom Hoxsie right.
    - A lone sea robin swims towards the light, seeking a path out of the entrapping web, May 1, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A lone sea robin swims towards the light, seeking a path out of the entrapping web. A primitive-looking fish with a bony skull and sharp spines, they are beautiful when they spread their wing-like fins. Ian Campbell left, Tom Hoxsie right.
    - The Amelia Bucolo returns to Point Judith after hauling her trap, June 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Amelia Bucolo returns to Point Judith after hauling her trap. Both the Bucolo and the Maria Mendonsa were built by Gladding and Hearn on the Taunton River in nearby Somerset, Massachusetts. Begun in 1955, the shipyard still builds steel and aluminum vessels, a rarity on the East Coast. The Bucolo, built in 1965, is still powered by her original Caterpillar 342 engine. Alan Glidden estimates her fuel consumption at five gallons per hour, burning a few hundred gallons every three weeks. Fishing, unlike many careers today, has always been a trade passed down by one generation to the next. Age and experience has taught youth and enthusiasm. While there are a few schools still offering some training in the business, most fishermen start on the back deck of a fishing boat willing to take them to sea. The fishing industry is democratic by nature. As a fisherman once told me, who you were, where you came from, or what you had previously done wasn't important. What mattered was how you did your job, and any fisherman who put in effort could expect to see results over time. Young workers once entered the trade dreaming of the vessel they would eventually command, and the majority of Rhode Island's fishing captains began their climb to the pilothouse from the lowest rung on the ladder.
    - Gear once again covers the wharf at the summer's end, October 15, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      Gear once again covers the wharf at the summer's end. Anchors, buoys, nets, line, and the vessels themselves are retired for winter. The season ends abruptly when quotas for the year are filled. Once over, the crew's last job before dispersing is to gather back this gear. The twine is removed from the frames and brought ashore for drying and storage. Frames come next—the thousands of yards of line and the buoys that kept the trap afloat throughout the summer months. Finally, the 1,000-pound anchors are swung aboard for the trip back to their winter home along the waterfront. In the past, companies employed trap crews of hundreds of men on a year-round basis. They often fished a longer season when weather allowed, and when fishing ended, there were still new traps to build and twine to repair. Today, small crews disband and look for new work to tide them over the long winter months. Some stay within the fisheries while others go ashore to jobs with no ties to the sea. Yachts moored in the harbor begin to disappear as the winter intrudes, and Sakonnet Point settles into the role of icy gatekeeper at the mouth of the bay, quiet and deserted until spring arrives once again.
    - A Parascandolo & Sons Trap Company truck sits at a barn located a few miles from Sakonnet Point, December 17, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      A Parascandolo & Sons Trap Company truck sits at a barn located a few miles from Sakonnet Point. The barn stores trap gear through the winter months. These stainless steel trailers are in big demand on the waterfront, not subject to the quick decay modern aluminum trailers face when exposed to the saltwater environment. Used not only to transport and store gear, many of them are refrigerated and hold daily catches until ready for shipment. As with any product, market prices vary with the demand for any particular species and the available supply. While allowed to catch fewer fish than in the past, higher prices in the marketplace for smaller quantities have helped offset some of the financial loss brought about by regulations. As waterfront property over the course of the last thirty years became more desirable, fishermen have been forced to move parts of their operations away from the ocean to more affordable locations, again increasing their costs. Housing for the wealthy continues to envelope the working waterfront and its supporting infrastructure. Newport, once a major fishing center, now caters only to yachtsmen and tourists. Even the loss of local hayfields to developers robs the trap fisherman of important space. Only time will tell how much longer this industry can survive.
    - The Maria Mendonsa's crew gathers the boats once again shortly after the morning's promising sunrise, April 18, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF
      The Maria Mendonsa's crew gathers the boats once again shortly after the morning's promising sunrise. The future of fishing in New England remains uncertain. As regulations pile upon the fisheries in the few ports remaining on the Eastern Seaboard, fishermen leave the work of generations to head inland in hopes of earning a living with a more certain future. What we lose as a society when they leave goes beyond the ability to buy fresh seafood from local sources. While we can, for now at least, buy seafood farmed or fished from countries located around our shrinking globe, there will come a day when we can no longer afford to freight our dinners from a spot on the ocean 6,000 miles distant. Beyond these considerations, however, is the loss of yet another industry, another working culture, and the people who once toiled to provide food for the rest. Over the past thirty years, our country has shed these types of jobs and skills in a relentless quest for cheaper products, and as we now begin to discover, without work to do ourselves, we can no longer afford the products we now import. When a few large corporations finally control the industry, the small businesses that each boat represents will fade away, as will the jobs they provide. These are the type of men and women who built our country: independent, hardworking, and self-motivated, and we will all share in the loss when they no longer work our coastlines.
    - Janet circles her offshore trap during her last season as a working vessel, May 23, 2008, afc2013031_dc002; 1 TIFF